Nicholas Ketz, PhD

Applied Research Scientist: Artificial Intelligence, Bioinformatics, Complex Systems, Human Studies

■ nick.ketz@gmail.com nickketz.github.io in www.linkedin.com/in/nickketz

Summary | Applied scientist developing machine learning solutions to advanced research problems. Interests in understanding and developing intelligent systems (human and artificial); analysis and visualization of complex, high-dimensional data; quantitative approaches to aesthetics and consciousness. Experience in academic and industrial research, product development and human studies.

RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

DNA Large Language Modeling Gene therapy, cross-species engineering	03/2022 - Present
Generative AI Video and images grounded in learned human concepts	01/2020 - 01/2022
Model Based Reinforcement Learning Agent based domain adaptation	01/2020 - 01/2022
Lifelong Deep Learning Sequential multi-task learning in deep neural networks	09/2018 - 01/2021
Closed-loop Neural Stimulation Device/algorithm development in humans	09/2016 - 06/2018

EDUCATION/EMPLOYMENT

Colossal Biosciences/Form Bio Principle AI/ML Scientist	02/2022 - Present
HRL Laboratories Research Scientist: Information and Systems Sciences	09/2016 - 01/2022
University Colorado, Boulder PhD: Computational Cognitive Neuroscience	09/2010 - 09/2016
New York University Research Assistant: Davachi Human Memory Lab	09/2007 - 07/2010
University Minnesota, Twin Cities BA:Physics, minor:Psychology	09/2003 - 06/2007

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Deep Learning | Convolutional, Recurrent, and Transformer Neural Networks. Deep Reinforcement Learning (model-free and model-based). Unsupervised learning (auxiliary tasks, semi-supervised)

Machine Learning | Non-differentiable Optimization (CMA-ES, MCMC), Probabilistic Inference (Clustering, Gaussian Process, Bayesian Optimization), Unsupervised Learning (KNN, PCA, ICA, t-SNE, UMAP)

Statistics | Parametric and non-parametric inference in linear and non-linear models: GLM, Random Effects, Bayesian, A/B (hypothesis) testing, time-series analysis, experimental design

Programming/Computing Packages | Python (PyTorch, Tensorflow, Numpy, Scipy, Scikit-Learn, Jupyter/Collab, HuggingFace), MATLAB, R, CUDA GPU, Git, Docker, AWS, GCP

SELECT PUBLICATIONS/PATENTS/WHITE PAPERS

US Patent 2024 | System and method for semantically grounded video generation

Sasha Strelnikoff, **Nicholas A Ketz**, Praveen K Pilly; Generative video Al system prompted by learned human concepts

White Paper 2022 | Model Interpretability Methods to Predict Gene Therapy Manufacturing Failures Nicholas Ketz; Extracting learned motifs from DNA sequence models predictive of gene therapy manufacturing failures

US Patent 2020 | System and method for optimized independent component selection for automated signal artifact removal to generate a clean signal

Nicholas Ketz, Matthew E Phillips, Praveen K Pilly; Scalable solution for removal of nuisance components in time-series data

ICLR 2019 | Sliced cramer synaptic consolidation for preserving deeply learned representations Soheil Kolouri, Nicholas Ketz, Andrea Soltoggio, Praveen K. Pilly; A novel framework for overcoming catastrophic forgetting by preserving the distribution of the network's output at an arbitrary layer